<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The righteousnes of God to man, wherein he was created; with a discovery of the fall, by the strength and subtilty of the serpent: and of the recovery of man, by the seed of the woman, which bruises the serpents head. Also, a declaration against the beast and his followers, who act by his power; and a warning to the people not to joyn with the beast, nor to uphold the harlot, least you be taken with the beast and the false prophet, and cast into the lake together alive, and there be none to deliver you. A few words to O. C. and to the officiers and souldiers of the army in general. With, a true declaration how I lived before I knew the truth, and how I came to know the truth, and overcame deceit. Given forth for the simples sake, that they may learn righteousness; ... / By a sufferer for the righteous seed sake, in the common goal of Edmonds Bury in Suffolk, who is called George Rofe.</title>
            <author>Rofe, George, d. 1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91924</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1788</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E885_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200681</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861361</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861361</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113494</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91924)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113494)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 133:E885[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The righteousnes of God to man, wherein he was created; with a discovery of the fall, by the strength and subtilty of the serpent: and of the recovery of man, by the seed of the woman, which bruises the serpents head. Also, a declaration against the beast and his followers, who act by his power; and a warning to the people not to joyn with the beast, nor to uphold the harlot, least you be taken with the beast and the false prophet, and cast into the lake together alive, and there be none to deliver you. A few words to O. C. and to the officiers and souldiers of the army in general. With, a true declaration how I lived before I knew the truth, and how I came to know the truth, and overcame deceit. Given forth for the simples sake, that they may learn righteousness; ... / By a sufferer for the righteous seed sake, in the common goal of Edmonds Bury in Suffolk, who is called George Rofe.</title>
                  <author>Rofe, George, d. 1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert at the Black-spread-Eagle at the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 7th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>God --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prisoners' writings, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113494:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE RIGHTEOUSNES OF GOD to MAN, wherein he was created; With a diſcovery of the fall, by the ſtrength and ſubtilty of the Serpent: And of the recovery of Man, by the ſeed of the Woman, which brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the Serpents Head.</p>
            <p>ALSO, A Declaration againſt the Beaſt and his followers, who act by his power; And a Warning to the people not to joyn with the Beaſt, nor to uphold the Harlot, leaſt you be taken with the Beaſt and the falſe Prophet, and caſt into the Lake toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alive, and there be none to deliver you.</p>
            <p>A few words to <hi>O. C.</hi> And to the Officiers and Souldiers of the Army in general.</p>
            <p>WITH, A true Declaration how I lived before I knew the truth, and how I came to know the truth, and overcame deceit.</p>
            <p>Given forth for the ſimples ſake, that they may learn Righteouſneſs; and to know him whom God hath given to be a Covenant to the People, and a light to the Gentiles, and his ſalvation to Redeem his ſeed from the ends of the earth, and all that come unto God by him, ſhall in no wiſe periſh, but have eternal life; But he is a ſtumbling-block, and a Rock of offence to the Nations; and bleſſed are they who are not offended in him.</p>
            <p>By a ſufferer for the righteous ſeed ſake, in the common Goal of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds Bury</hi> in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> who is called GEORGE ROFE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the Black-ſpread-Eagle at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113494:2"/>
            <head>The Righteouſneſs of God to Man, wherein he was Created; with a Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the Fall, by the ſtrength and ſubtilty of the Serpent, and of the Recovery of Man, by the Seed of the Woman, which bruiſes the Serpents Head.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Beginning God Created every Creature, and ſaw that the work of his hands was good; God is good, and all Creatures in Heaven and Earth, and the Seas, and all them, and all that in them was, was made in the beginning by the Word of God; and all proceeded from God, and was good; and God created man in his own Image, and made him good; and of him who was good he made the Woman, and ſhe was one with the Man, and they were good; and God placed them in the Garden, wherein he lived and walked; and <hi>Adam</hi> was the Son of God, and lived and walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with God in the habitation of God, and God made him Lord over all the works of his hands, and gave him dominion over every Creature, that they might ſerve him; and in the wiſdome of God, while he walked with God, he ruled over the Creatures of God; and in the Garden, God gave him e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Beaſt,, and Fowl, and Fiſh; and out of the earth, he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed every Hearb and every Tree to grow, and there was no bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſs among them, for their Seed was in themſelves; and the Tree of Knowledge he alſo made which was good but not for food, and therefore God forbad Man to eat of it; and made a Law with Man, that in the day he eat thereof, he ſhould
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113494:3"/>die; and God gave Man of every Tree that was good for food, to be his food, and Man had power to rule, and ruled over e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Creature, and walked with God in the place of his dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, where there was no iniquity nor evil; and the Serpent was more ſubtil than any Beaſt of the field, and fell from God, and became a lyar, Gods enemie, and he knew that God had ſaid to Man that he ſhould not eat of the Tree in the midſt of the Garden, (the Tree of Knowledge of good and evill) and he talked with the Woman concerning it, and what God had ſaid unto them of it; and ſhe knew the Command of God that they were not to eat of it, nor to touch it, and in the day they eat thereof, God promiſed they ſhould die; and the Serpent who was a Lyar, ſaid they ſhould not die, and of the fruit which was not good for food gave the Woman to eat, and was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaved in the Woman, and got power over the Woman, and ſhe did eat, and entered into him who was the power of death, and acted by his power and deceaved the Man, ſo they both fell from God, firſt the Woman was deceaved then the Man, and here the Serpent got power, and ſlew the Lambe; and the World was ſet in Mans heart, and here Man loſt his power and purity from being the Son of God, and was as God, but not of God, but had entered into the knowledge and taſte of evill, and fell from God, and became a likeneſs as God; and here was the founder of Images and the ground of Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and death, and hell, and the grave had power over Man, and ſhame came upon Man, and their garment was taken away, and nakedneſs appeared, and fear entered, and Man became fearfull to ſee God, but God fulfilled his promiſe which was righteous, and death came upon them, and in the Curſe were they driven out from God, to till the earth, which was accurſed for their tranſgreſſion ſake, and labour and pain were they cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be in, and God curſed the Serpent above every Beaſt of the field, and drove the curſed out of the Garden, and ſet a flaming Sword which turned every way, to keep the way of the Tree of Life, and that the curſed ſhould not enter the Garden, and promiſed the ſeed of the Woman to bruiſe the Serpents head, which was known in <hi>Abell,</hi> whom <hi>Cain</hi> who was brought forth in the Curſe, ſlew, him who was not in the Curſe, but
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113494:3"/>knew the ſeed of the Woman which God had promiſed to bruiſe the Serpents head, and knew God and walked righteouſly with God, and was accepted above <hi>Cain,</hi> who was in the Curſe, unto whoſe Sacrifice God had no reſpect, through he offered that which was good, but not in the good, ſo out of the faith, ſo to him it was ſin, and he did not well, and ſin laid at his door: and God gave another ſeed in <hi>Abells</hi> ſtead, <hi>Seth,</hi> in whom the ſeed of the Woman was known, and the Serpents head brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and the World deſtroyed, and the Lambe raiſed to Life, which in him and his ſeed took away the ſins of the World; and <hi>Enoch</hi> walked with God, and God took him, and <hi>Noah</hi> and his Sons walked in the faith of the ſeed of the Woman, and they and their Wives were ſaved, with the Male and with the Female of the Creatures, which were not deſtroyed with the old World, who lived in the delight of beauty, and pride, and luſt, and were builded upon the Serpent, and therein all fleſh was corrupted, and they run a whoring after the thoughts of the immaginations of their own hearts, which was evill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually, for which the wrath of God was kindled againſt them, and in his fury he ſwept them away in the flood of his Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but God reſpected the ſeed which walked in truth, and ſaved them from the deſtruction which he brought upon the wicked; and made a Covenant with <hi>Noah,</hi> not to drown the earth any more, nor to cut off all fleſh by the floods of water, and ſet his bow in the clouds for a ſign unto generations per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually; and <hi>Noah</hi> and his Sons was bleſſed and had power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all Beaſts and creeping things, and the Fiſhes in the Sea, and all that moved upon the earth was given into their hands; but <hi>Ham</hi> in whom the Serpent had his ſeat, did that which was evill, and upon his Son <hi>Canaan</hi> the Curſe entered, and againſt his off-ſpring the Curſe prevailed, and they were not accepted among the ſeed, but were driven out before the ſeed which was bleſſed, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.11. and <hi>Lot</hi> who was of the ſeed was ſaved from being deſtroyed with <hi>Sodome;</hi> and his Daughters who were in the faith of the ſeed, were ſaved from being deſtroyed, yet they did evill, they conſulted with the Serpent, and fed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Tree of Knowledge, and brought forth a ſeed in the Curſe which was accurſed, whoſe off-ſpring is accurſed unto
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113494:4"/>this day, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.34. <hi>Numb.</hi> 24 17. <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.11. And <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> who was the Father of the faithful, receaved the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God unto the ſeed, and that in <hi>Iſaac</hi> all kindreds of the earth ſhould be bleſſed, and with <hi>Jacob</hi> did God eſtabliſh his Covenant, that he made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and bleſſed him and gave his Brethren to be his ſervants, and ſuſtained him with all that was good in the earth, and he was of the ſeed, and was Ruler over all his Brethern, (as of <hi>Iſhmael</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> and their off-ſprings) but lives and raigns with God for ever, and to his ſeed is the bleſſing for ever: and God promiſed that his ſeed ſhould multiply and be a great people and reach to the ends of the earth; And <hi>Moſes</hi> was of the ſeed, who choſe rather to ſuffer affliction with the People of God, than to enjoy the pleaſure of ſin for a ſeaſon, by whoſe hand God wrought won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully, and delivered his ſeed out of the houſe of Bondage, and out of the Land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and cauſed the waters to ſtand on heapes, till the ſeed went over and was preſerved, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered out of the hands of their oppreſſors, and overthrew <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roah</hi> and his Hoſt in their ſight; (and them who were deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> who were not faithful to the ſeed, God cut off in the wilderneſs, and brought plagues upon them that mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mured,) and thus God wrought wonderfully by the hand of his Servant <hi>Moſes,</hi> whom he ſpake unto face to face, and promiſed that he would raiſe up a Prophet of his Brethren, like unto him, and him the People ſhould hear; and them that will not hearken to the words of this Prophet, which God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands to ſpeak, God will require it at their hands; and unto <hi>David</hi> who was of the ſeed, a man who walked in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, according to Gods own heart; God promiſed that out of his Loyns, and of his ſeed, he would raiſe up a Saviour of the People, which was fulfilled in the daies of <hi>Herod</hi> the King; and in <hi>Bethalem</hi> in <hi>Judea</hi> the Citie of <hi>David,</hi> was the Saviour born according to the promiſe, and there was the ſeed born; Jeſus a Saviour of his People from their ſins: who is ſet for the fall and riſing again of many in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and for a ſigne to be gaineſaid; who was and is a gin and a ſnare, and a ſtumbling block, and a rock of offence to the Nations, and bleſſed are them who are not offended in him, in whom is the promiſe to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113494:4"/>
               <hi>Iſaac</hi> fulfilled; and in him is all the Nations and kindreds of the earth called and bleſſed; and before him went the voyce of one crying in the wilderneſſe, <hi>Prepare yee the way of the Lord, and make his paths ſtraight,</hi> which was propheſied of by <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> and he was the voyce of the living God, ſent to prepare the way of his Son, and <hi>John</hi> witneſſed that he himſelf was not the light, but that Chriſt Jeſus was the true light, which lighteth every man that cometh into the world; and there was the fulfilling of the promiſes ſpoken by <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> 42.6, 7. and 49.6.9. And in thoſe dayes God gave his Son to be his ſalvation, to redeem his ſeed from the ends of the earth, and this Son of God is to be heard and ſubmitted to, and every one that will not ſubmit to his government, which is to eternity, ſhall be cut off and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh for ever. And now all people return to the Lord God, and liſten to the light of his onely Son in your conſciences, which ſhews you ſin and evil, which God hath given to redeem all that believe in it; and all that receive the light Chriſt Jeſus, the onely begotten Son of God, they receive power to become the ſons of God. He came unto his own, and his own received him not; to them he was a ſtumbling-block, becauſe they believed not in him: but all that believed in him, or that do believe in him, to them he is the great power of God unto ſalvation. The Lord God loved the world, and gave his onely begotten Son a light to open the blind eyes, to bring the priſoners out of the priſon-houſe, and is the gift of God, and leads captivity cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, that as many as believe in him ſhould not periſh, but have eternall life; and this life is in himſelf, who is the ſeed of God; who redeems all them that believe in the light, and walk in the light, which is of himſelf into himſelfe, out of the curſe, out of the world, out of the fall into Paradiſe from whence man fell; and from under his power who is the ſtrength of the fall, to ſerve him, to follow him, to walk in his light, to receive the light of life, and makes them of the ſeed which hath power to come through the Cherubims and the flaming ſword, into the Garden unto the Tree of Life, and to eat of it and live for ever. But all you that live in pride and idleneſſe, and luſt and uncleanneſſe; the light in your conſciences ſhewes you, that you are not of the ſeed, for the ſeed of the woman keeps the commands of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12 17.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113494:5"/>and all that is not of the ſeed, ſhall not enter into the Garden, nor cannot come neer the tree of life, nor have no right to it: ſo you are in the enmity of the wicked one, and ſhall never enter into the inheritance of the righteous. And all you hireling teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, you that preach for hire, and divine for money, and live in ungodly covetouſneſs, which is Idolatry, and tell people that they that miniſter at the Altar, ſhould live of the Altar, and that they that preach the Goſpel ſhould live of the Goſpel, the light in your conſciences alſo lets you ſee that you are not of the ſeed, nor know not the ſeed, but are in the enmity of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one againſt the ſeed, and are not ſent by Chriſt the ſeed to miniſter to the ſeed, nor do not miniſter at the Altar, nor live of the Altar; but your miniſtery is to them who are proud and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous, wicked ones like your ſelves, who are not the Altar, and on them you live and know not the Altar, and your preaching is not the Goſpel; if it were, then you would live of the Gſpel, and not of the world: But the ground and effect of your preaching, ſtands in the love of mony, and to tell that people cannot be freed from ſin in this life, and ſo preach that which the Apoſtles prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched not, and ſow that which is accurſed, and the love of mony is the root of all evill, and you live of the world and not of the Goſpel, and you are chargeable to the world, and oppreſs the people who are not of the Goſpel, and are out of the life of the Miniſters that the Goſpel ſent forth, who freely received and freely gave: But your preaching is not free, but for gifts and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, the wages of unrighteouſneſs, as the falſe Prophets ever was: and herein you are to periſh, as they did, who are out of the life of the ſeed, as you are who are their off-ſpring, which is accurſed for ever. And all people that deſire to know the truth of God, and that your ſouls ſhould be redeemed from under the power of the Divel, return to the light of Chriſt, which ſhews the ſeed of the Serpent, and the works of the Divell, and the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs that is acted by his power in you, that with the light you may be brought to know a difference between the ſeed of the Serpent and the ſeed of the Woman, which is promiſed to bruiſe the Serpents head; and ſearch and examine with the light of Chriſt in you, with it to ſee were you are, and how fat you are redemed out of the curſe, and out of that nature wherein the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113494:5"/>evill doer lodges, over which the curſe hath power; the fruits that is brought forth by the ſeed of the Serpent, are curſed fruits, and proceed from a curſed ground, and are brought forth in the curſe, and the actors of them are to periſh under the curſe and wrath of God; the luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eye, and pride and covetouſneſs, and ſwearing, and drunkenneſs, and all manner of uncleanneſs, and ſporting, and gaming, and fighting and quarrelling, and mocking and ſcoffing, and ſcorning, and all manner of prophaneſs, are the fruits of the Serpent, and are brought forth by his ſeed, which is in the curſe alienated from God in the kingdome of darkneſs, over which the ſeed of the woman hath power it to deſtroy: And this ſeed is known by them who are guided by the light of truth, which leads into all truth, and to deny the Serpent who is deceit, and the leader of the wicked in deceit; and the children of light doe by the power of Chriſt the light, follow the ſeed of the woman, and doe receive the light of life, and know the enmity put between the ſeed of the ſerpent and the ſeed of the woman, and know the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God, and obey him in his light, and by his power deny the Divell the Prince of death, and differ from him and his fruits, and are acquainted with his wiles, and know his motions to evill, and deny them, and know a difference with God from him who is Gods enemy, and know the worſhip of God in ſpirit and truth, and differ from them who pretend to worſhip him in their wills by traditions of men, and imaginations from the Scriptures, and not in ſpirit and truth, which worſhip God doth not accept.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <head>A Declaration againſt the Beaſt and his followers who are by his power, and a warning to the people not to joyn with the Beaſt, nor to uphold the Harlot, leſt you be taken with the Beaſt, and the falſe Prophet, and caſt all into the lake together alive, and there be none to deliver you.</head>
            <p>VVO unto them that are carried upon the Beaſt, and decree unrighteous Decrees, and by his power accompliſh them: ſuch haſten down to the pit in the way of perdition, by the ſtrength of the Dragon, the Divell and Satan that old Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, who goeth about as a roaring Lion, and deceiveth the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113494:6"/>who by his ſtrength and ſubtilty deceiveth the whole earth, and all that worſhip him they receive his mark in their foreheads, or in their right hands, and by his power make war with the remnant of the ſeed of the woman, who cannot worſhip nor bow down to the Beaſt nor his image, and ſeekes their lives to ſwallow them up quick, if by their power it might be, and to the uttermoſt of their power they proceed againſt the Lamb and his choſen, who follow him whitherſoever he goeth, and by the power of the Beaſt, who hath received his power and ſeat from the Dragon; doe they who worſhip the Beaſt, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the Saints the tribe of the Lamb, and overcome them, and caſt them into priſons and dungeons, and holes till they die; and ſome they ſcourge, and ſtock, and ſtone, and beat, and buffet, and ſpit upon, and hale out of the Synagogues to before Rulers, who have impriſoned them till their lives have been a ranſome to have ſet them at liberty with the Lamb; and this Beaſt reignes over the whole earth, and gives power to the inhabitants of the earth for to accompliſh his will to the utmoſt, that he might reign over all, and that the Lamb ſhould not take away their ſins; but that they ſhould take and drink of the cup of abomination and filthineſſe of his fornication to the bottome. But the Lamb will ariſe as a fierce Lion, and rule over the Nations with a rod of Iron, and daſh all the inhabitants of the earth to pieces who worſhip the Beaſt, and give them the cup of the fierceneſſe of his wrath to drink without mixture, and will reward the Harlot double according to her abominations and fornications, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſhe makes all nations of the earth drunk for her pleaſure, and they fared delitiouſly with her; but her kingdom ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a deſolation for ever. The Lamb of God which takes away the ſins of the world, he is the light of the world, and lightneth every man that cometh into the world, by which light all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and tongues and people may ſee the Beaſt which makes war againſt the Lamb: the light of the Lamb Chriſt Jeſus ſhews eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that they ſhould not live in wickedneſs, and reproves eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that do commit evill; and the Beaſt lodges in man, and leads in evill, and warres in man againſt the light of the Lamb, and they who joyn with the Beaſt, they joyn with the father of all miſchief, who leads in the way that is broad which leadeth to deſtruction, wherein all the world walks and wonders after
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113494:6"/>the Beaſt, and worſhips him, and know not whither they goe; who if they goe on in wickedneſs, are to have their reward with the Beaſt and the falſe Prophet, who are to be caſt into the lake alive, and there to be tormented day and night for ever and ever. And all people as you tender the good of your ſouls, return to the light of Chriſt in you, that by it you may learn what repentance is, and what the fear of the Lord is, and come out of Babylon from amongſt the wicked, that you may be recived of the Lord, and joyn not with the Beaſt, nor hold not up the Harlot any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, leſt you periſh. If you joyn with ſuch as call themſelves Miniſters, who have learned at <hi>Cambridge</hi> or <hi>Oxford,</hi> and call them the well-heads of Divinity, you uphold the Harlot, for in them places ſhe hath her ſeat, and by her power are they Prieſts come forth, and are of her and taught by her, and have learned of her, the Harlot, Myſtery, Babylon, which ſits upon the waters, which rides upon the Beaſt, who lodgeth in the waters, you peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are the waters, and in you the Beaſt lodges, which is one with the Harlot which makes war againſt the light of the Lamb in you, and with you do her Merchants trade, and to you doe her Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants ſell their ware, and of you do they take money, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with maintain themſelves, and wives and children in pride and idleneſs, and none live higher in luſt and pride, and fulneſs of bread than they, and hence you may ſee them to be an ill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to all that follow them, and by their lies and lightneſs do they make the people light and vain, and all that ever they doe or ſpeak of the name of the Lord, it is in vain, and by it none learns righteouſneſs, but the image of the Beaſt is upheld by them, and in them hath a mouth, &amp; ſpeakes great ſwelling words of vanity, by which the people are deceived, &amp; none by them is turned from comitting all evill; but have been a long time learning, &amp; not yet come to the knowledge of the pure truth, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is but one, wherein wayfaring men may walk &amp; not err. And againſt you, O ye prieſts, is the ſtrong arm of the Almighty ſtretched forth, which wil rout you out root and branch, and you ſhall have your portion with your King the Angel of the bottomleſs pit, who leads you now in your curſed practices, to preach for gifts and rewards, for which you have ſold your ſelves to your King, who hath long led you after the reward of unrighteouſneſs, and for it ſets you on work to uphold his kingdom; and you by his power ſtrive to the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113494:7"/>utmoſt ſo to doe, and go to your brethren who have received the ſame power, and they joyned with you, and perſecute and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon them who freely are ſent of the Lord to declare againſt ſuch ungodly practices. But the Lord God is bringing forth his Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Army againſt you, who are fierce and terrible, and ſhall ſpread over the whole earth, and their Inſtruments are new, and have teeth, and ſhall daſh down you and your King and your king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and the breath of the living God ſhall conſume you root and branch: this Army is ſtrengthened by the Almighty God, and he is with them, and they fear not the Nations, for no ſword can enter them, nor no weapon formed againſt them can proſper, nor the mighty men cannot hinder them; for the conqueſt is theirs, and all the Nations of the earth is but as a Potters veſſell before them; for their leader is juſt, holy and true, and they are called and Choſen and Faithful, and are reſolved to make an utter deſolation of Antichriſt and his kingdome, of whom you Prieſts are and he you ſeek to uphold and are againſt Chriſt in the wayes of <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Balaam,</hi> and your way is to perdition. <hi>Judas</hi> ſold the Lamb of God to your Fathers, who ſlew him and bought a field with the reward of iniquity; and you ſell the words that proceeded from the Lamb, and therein are ſwallowed up in ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and have purchaſed many fields with the mony you have had for his words whom your fathers ſlew, and your tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is exceeding much greater than <hi>Judaſſes,</hi> with the reward of whoſe iniquity there was one field bought, but you have bought many fields, beſides what you have ſpent upon your luſts in main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining your ſelves, and wives and children in pride and idleneſs, &amp; fulneſs of bread, the ſins of <hi>Sodom,</hi> by whom the Lord of life is crucified, and the plagues of God will be heavier upon you than upon <hi>Judas,</hi> who is gone before you to his and your home, and God hath already curſed your bleſſings, and your preaching is noyſome in his ſight, and your ſinging is loathſome to be heard which ſtands all in unrighteouſneſs, for which the wrath of God for ever is turned againſt you and your ſeed, which will be ſwept away with the beſome of deſtruction; yea already the whirlwind of the Lord is gone forth againſt you; and you all from the leaſt to the greateſt cannot eſcape it, and the fire which will devour you for your iniquities ſake, and the blood of thouſands who have periſhed under your Miniſtry, who were ever learning of you, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113494:7"/>knew not the truth, is upon you, and at your hands God will require it: and all that truſt to your teaching are like to be loſt for want of knowledge: and in this I am a witneſs for God. And this I am ready to ſeal with my blood if I be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="message">
            <head>A few words to <hi>O. C.</hi> and to the Officers and Souldiers of the Army in general.</head>
            <p>TO thee <hi>Oliver Crumwell,</hi> thus ſaith the Lord, I had cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen thee amongſt the thouſands in the Nations, to execute my wrath upon my enemies, and gave them to thy ſword with which I fought for the zeal of my own name, &amp; gave thee the enemies of my own ſeed to be a curſe and a reproach for ever, and made thee an inſtrument againſt them, and drove many of them out before thee, and thou haſt taken the ſpoyl of them, and many have I cut down by my ſword in thy hand, that my wrath might be executed againſt them to the utmoſt; and therein for a time thou was zealous, and then I was with thee for my ſeeds ſake: but thou art fallen from thy firſt inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, and in the ſpoyl of my enemies art exalted, and art ſet up in the glory of the world, which is not pleaſant in my ſight; for therefore drove I my enemies out, and ruined them before thee, that my ſeed might be ſet at liberty, and have its freedom in the Nations to worſhip me: But now thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardeſt me not with good for the good I have done to thee; but in thy name and by thy power doe my pure ſeed ſuffer, and tyrants rule over my people; and by thy power and in thy name doe they perſecute them, and impriſon them unto the death, and have ſpilled the blood of my innocent people to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie their corrupt deſires. But ſurely I will viſit for theſe things, and much doe they lie upon thee; and if thou letteſt tyrants get rule in thy name, and by thy power, on thee and thy ſeed will I require the blood of the innocent that hath been ſhed in theſe late dayes under thy government, and will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113494:8"/>my people by my own power, and thou ſhalt know that I have ſpoken to thee when I viſit for thoſe ſufferings of my people, then thou ſhalt not be able to plead ignorance, but ſhalt know that thou haſt been warned of them, and that I gave thee a time to repent.</p>
            <p>ANd all you Officers of the Army from the higheſt to the loweſt, and all Souldiers, know, that God drove out his enemies before you; not for your ſakes, but for his own name ſake, which long hath been polluted by the heathen; and them that God overthrew in his wrath, it was for his own ſeeds ſake that they might have their liberty, and not for your ſakes who are turned againſt the Lord and his ſeed, and are exalted in the pride of life, and in the ſame glory wherein the enemies of God were who are drove out and made a curſe and reproach for ever. Remember how God wrought in the dayes of old for his ſeeds ſake, and how he delivered his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of the land of Egypt, not by the ſtrength of fleſh and blood, but by his own power, wherewith he hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrown the multitudes of Horſes and their Riders, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered his people, and them who were delivered out of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, who in the wilderneſs turned from the Lord, he there cut off: and you are turned into the ſame Idolatry for which they were cut off. Your hearts run a whoring af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter other lovers then God; you eate and drink and riſe up and play, you are exalted in pride, and glory in your own ſtrength, and do not give God the glory for what he hath done for you, but follow the example of the Kings of Babylon, to whom God gave power that they ſhould deſtroy his enemies. And remember what God did to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> who had grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter power than you, for his power reached over the whole earth, and whom he would he let live, and whom he would he ſlew. And after that he was exalted, &amp; gloried in the ſtrength &amp; pride of himſelf (<hi>Dan.</hi> 4) &amp; gave not God the glory, and God drove him out from amongſt men, and changed his heart from mans, and gave to him a beaſts heart, and wetted him with the dew of heaven, and he was fed with graſſe till ſeven times
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113494:8"/>paſſed over him, and till he knew that the Lord god reigned. And hence you may ſee how God reſiſteth the proud; and here you may ſee that neither the ſtrength of fleſh, of men nor horſes, can deliver the proud out of the hand of the Almighty God, who will reign over all. And remember <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> how he made a feaſt, and drank wine in abundance, and how God cut him off, and gave his kingdome to <hi>Darius</hi> the Midian, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was weighed and found too light, <hi>Dan.</hi> 5. And here you may ſee your figure, and know that you are in the ſame nature, and are too light. And remember how the Kings of Aſſyria ſpoyled the Nations, and beat down their idols: and to do this, God gave them power that they ſhould execute his wrath upon the heads of his enemies, though for doing it they had not a reward with the righteous, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1.37. But the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyrians gloried in their own ſtrength; and in blaſphemy did <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> come up againſt the Lords anointed, and gloried for the King of Aſſyria in the multitude of his Chariots, and they truſted in their own ſtrength, and in the pride of their hearts came up againſt the ſeed of the living God; and God delivered his own ſeed, and ſent his Angel who ſmot the Aſſyrians, &amp; cut off an hundred fourſcore and five thouſand: and thus God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered his people by his own power, and not by the ſtrength of man. And thus God ſlew and cut off his enemies, and aven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his quarrell againſt his adverſaries, whom he had made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments in times before to cut down his enemies, and when they were lifted up in pride, then God abaſed them; &amp; when they gloried in their own ſtrength, then God cut them down. And all you while you have time ſpend it not in vanity, and glory not in pride, nor truſt in your own ſtrength, for if you do, ſurely God wil abaſe you &amp; cut you off, for you are not greater than them whom God hath cut off for ſo doing. And every one fear the living God and dread his name, and live not in pride and vanity, and uſe not violence to any man, but be content with your wages, for God will reward you according to your works, and will ſurely puniſh you if you oppreſſe his people, and all that you take by fraud God wil judge you for, and while there is yet a day given you to repent in, take heed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113494:9"/>how you deſpiſe it, leſt God cut you off in your iniquities, and your periſh; and know this, that God will deliver his own ſeed out of the hands of tyrants, though his people for a time doe now ſuffer in innocency by you and your power, and the powers of the earth; yet a time of deliverance will come, and woe to them that are their oppreſſors or that joyn with them that doe oppreſs them, for they ſhall receive a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward according to their works, and God will deliver his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple himſelfe, and they ſhall reign over all their enemies for ever and ever. And in the aſſurance of this hope and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence I reſt where man cannot make me afraid.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <head>Here followeth a true Declaration how I lived before I knew the truth, how I came to know the truth, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came deceit.</head>
            <p>FOr many years together in my youth I lived after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Heathen, in pride and vanity, and ſporting and gaming, and propaneſſe, and much wantonneſſe, as the common prophane ones in the world now doe; whereby the Juſt, the light of Chriſt in me, was ſlaine, and the Covenant of God trode under foot by the power of the Beaſt; which guided me in wickedneſs, and oftentimes by that time I was twelve years of age, the witneſſe of God the light of Chriſt in me did ariſe, and judge and codemne me for my wickedneſſe. And oftentimes I was ſmot by the witneſs of God, ſo that terror came upon me, that I have not known what to doe, but have been ſmot by the hand of the Lord into many fears of what ſhould become of me here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113494:9"/>and have often wept exceedingly in ſecret and in my bed, ſo that I have wetted much clothes with teares. But when I was among my kindred after the fleſh, or among other heatheniſh company, the Beaſt acted ſo ſtrongly, and led me ſo much, that I was aſhamed to tell any what I ailed; but rather ſubmitted to the power of the Beaſt, to joyn with the Heathen in wickedneſs, than to tell them that I had been in torment for my wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p>And thus I went on in rebellion againſt the light of my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience from time to time, though I knew by it I did not that which was right, and was condemned in my conſcience for what I did daily contrary to the light: And one time I was ſmot with terror down to the earth, ſo that I cryed out exceedingly for a long time together, and lay with my face towards the earth, and could not for a time be comforted, terror was ſo great upon me. And yet for all this the Beaſt got up in me, and ſtrongly acted me in the like wickedneſs for which the judgements of God had often been upon me, and I could not ſee any way how to eſcape the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which the Divell daily led me into, but gave my ſelfe to reading much in the Scriptures; and yet the power of the wicked one prevailed againſt me, ſo that I received no ſtrength againſt him by the knowledge of the Scriptures, though the Scriptures ſhewed me in part what I ſhould doe, yet the power againſt ſin was not there to be found; but ſinne got the upper hand and ruled over me, and therein I was led captive, and made a prey upon by the Divell who deceived me through ſubtilty. And when I had read and ſtudied what I could in my own will for many yeares together, I could not find out a way to know God, nor ſatisfaction to my ſoul; but judgement followed me, and my thoughts accuſed me, and the light witneſſed againſt me, ſo peace I had not found in all that ever I did ſeek out, but fear purſued me, and often in the night time, teares run from my eyes, and terror laid hold on me; ſo that I have been made to pray exceedingly; but I knew not to whom, but according as I had heard or read, but no anſwer I ſaw though I called out often; yet I knew not that God
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113494:10"/>whom I called to, nor that Chriſt in whoſe name I thought I asked; but into a profeſſion of God, and Chriſt, and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, I was led by the will of the fleſh, though I was a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to the life of God and godlineſs: And in this profeſſion not knowing the power of God, I walked neer three yeares, and wandred about therein to profeſſors of the world like my ſelf, and went to Prieſts where they preached, and heard them two or three times a week commonly and long toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and yet fear purſued me, and peace I could not find, though I ſought it with tears often, yet the way of peace I knew not, but diſſention and miſery was in my paths, and the feare of God I lived out of, though then I lived in a profeſſion, and was covered with much ſubtilty, ſo that the world could not ſee but that I lived orderly, and I was kept from many com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon pollutions of the world, though the Beaſt acted me, and often would have led me into greater abominations than he did, had not the witneſs of God often brought judgement &amp; terror upon me, and iudged deceit before it was acted. And in this profeſſion of words I was at times exalted, and therein lived in pride and vainglory, and was lifted up in that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge by which the witneſſe of God was ſlain, and I led in great darkneſs: and when I was exalted moſt, then greateſt darkneſs entred in upon me, in which profeſſion I found no peace, neither could I, for wickedneſs was lined in, and the profeſſion was not of God (though it was like what the Saints had profeſſed and lived the life of) as all the worlds profeſſion is, who follows the Beaſt, who leads them in imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of that which the Saints and ſervants of God did by command from God. And when I was about the age of twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years old, when I was at the height of my profeſſion, in which my ſoul found no reſt, it happened that according to the will of God, there came ſome of his meſſengers (who were called Quakers) to the town where I lived in my empty pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; (<hi>Halſteed</hi> in <hi>Eſſex</hi>) wherein I was not ſatisfied, but went into the Market to hear the people called Quakers ſpeak; who ſpoke there ſome few words which I did not then underſtand, though I had heard ſomething of them in writing,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113494:10"/>and many ſlanderous reports; yet I was convinced in my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience that they were the people of God: and the Scriptures witneſſed that the people of God ſhould be hated and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, and all manner of evill ſpoken of them. So yet I was not at reſt in my ſpirit, but deſired to know the truth and the life of it. And ſoon after that time the Lord ſent another of his Meſſengers who had a meeting in that town where I lived, and in, the forepart of the day came to the ſteeple-houſe, where I was hearing one of the worlds Miniſters, who is cal'd <hi>William Sparrow,</hi> who had long deceived me with good words and fair ſpeeches: and when he had ended his ſpeaking, the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger of God ſpoke, and reached the witneſs of God in me, ſo I was drawn in love towards him, and the later part of the day went to hear him ſpeak, and his words reached the witneſs of God in me, ſo that I was more exceedingly drawn out in love towards him, and heard more to my ſouls ſatisfaction that day, than ever before: and that of God in me, which often had iudged me, and brought feares upon me, owned his words, and owned him to be of God, and the ſeed of God in me was refreſhed and grew, and ſhewed me how I had ſpent my time, and brought all the evil that ever I remember I acted, and laid it before me, and condemned me for it, which condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I was made willing to own, and therein did wait for the mercies of God, &amp; the ſeed of God in me grew in ſtrength, and ſhewed me what I ſhould doe, and what I ſhould leave un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, and was my guide to guide me out of the former igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and wickedneſs I had lived in, and was a Judge for God to condemn the ground of the moſt ſecret deceit in me; and ſhewed me the moſt ſecret deceit of the Serpent, and gave me power to withſtand all wickedneſs; which before I owned the light of Chriſt, I had not power to withſtand, the ſtrength of the enemy had ſuch power over me. And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that God had ſhewed me the way of truth, and gave me power to withſtand all evill, the Divel was exceeding wroth againſt me, and wrought exceeding ſubtilly to have deſtroyed that which was begotten of God in me; but the gift of God was plenteous, and grew, and ſhaked terribly the earth, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113494:11"/>removed mountains', and rewarded the tranſgreſſor with judgement, and caſt out the Prince of this world, and reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for God going on conquering, and to conquer, and treads down all Gods enemies under his feet. And this is the free mercy and love of God that he hath revealed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to me by the light of his own Son, and hath made known his everlaſting Covenant of peace to me, and hath redeemed my ſoul out of hell, and from under the power of the Divell into the glory of his own Son, to praiſe him in the beauty of holineſs in mount Sion for ever, who hath called me by his own Spirit and power, to bear witneſs for his own name in righteouſneſs, and hath given me his word to declare to the inhabitants of the earth; and his power to ſtop the mouthes of truths gain-ſayers, and to confound the falſe Prophets, and make the Deviners mad, and to judge all hirelings and falſe teachers out from amongſt the Saints.</p>
            <p>This is the work which the Lor hath done for his ſeeds ſake which dwells in me; which he hath raiſed to eternall life, to live and reign with him for ever. And it was his free love that he left a ſeed in me, elſe I had been to him as the Cities of <hi>Sodom</hi> and as the inhabitants of <hi>Gomorrah.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The world calls me <hi>George Rofe,</hi> but my name is written in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and therein do I rejoyce.</signed>
               <dateline>From the common Goal of <hi>Emonds Bury</hi> in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> wherein I have ſuffered more than <hi>40</hi> weeks for the truth
<date>this laſt day of the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> moneth, <hi>1656.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
